National Organization for Women, New York State Chapter; Records apap029
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
National Organization for Women (NOW), New York State Chapter Records1966-1988
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
National Organization for Women. New York Chapter
apap029
23.75 cubic ft.
The state chapter of NOW aims to bring women into full participation in the mainstream of American society in order to exercise all privileges and responsibilities in an equal partnership with men.
Administrative History
The New York State Chapter of the National Organization for Women, the first state chapter to be chartered in the United States, was founded on February 6, 1967. The New York State Chapter has the same purpose as the National Organization: to bring women into full participation in the mainstream of American society in order to exercise all privileges and responsibilities in an equal partnership with men. This purpose includes equal rights and responsibilities in all aspects of citizenship, public service, employment, education, and family life, as well as freedom from discrimination because of age, marital status, sexual preference, and parenthood [NOW-NYS Chapter By-laws, 1976, folder Bylaws, 1976-77, President's Subject Files].
In 1974 NOW-New York State adopted by-laws defining the constituent element of its structure which consisted of members, member chapters, State Council, State Executive Committee, State Council Committees, State Task Forces, and the State Convention. The New York Chapter is overseen by the Executive Committee, made up of bi-annually elected officers who are composed of the President, Executive Vice-President, Secretary, Treasurer, and three members whose portfolio was to be determined [NOW-NYS Bylaws (adopted November, 1974), folder State Council, 1973-74, State Council Meetings series]. The revised 1976 by-laws defined the responsibilities of the three additional Executive Committee members and created two new positions: Vice-President of Membership, Vice-President for Legislation, Financial Vice-President, Vice-President of Public Information, and the Chairperson of the State Council. The Executive Committee forms the decision-making body at State Council meetings. The State Council is made up of two delegates from each local Chapter of the New York State Chapter, the Executive Committee Officers, and State Task Force heads. The State Council meets at least three times a year in Albany. The Albany Area Chapter was formed in January 1972, and subsequently became the central office for New York State.
The Chairperson of the State Council presides over the Council meetings, while the president presides at all State Executive Committee meetings and at the State Convention.
The State Convention is the general membership assembly of New York, responsible for formulation of general policy and program priorities. State Task Forces are approved and appointed by the Executive Committee. [NOW-NYS Chapter By-laws, 1976].
NOW-New York State Presidents
Eileen Kelly, 1974-77
Zelle Andrews, 1977-1979
Sheila Molnar Feiger, 1979-82
Theresa Bergen, 1982-84
Noreen Connell, 1984-1988
Marilyn Fitterman, 1988-1992
Sharon Fawly, 1992-1996
Lois Shapiro Canter, 1996-2000
Kathryn Lake Mazierski, 2000-2004
Marcia Pappas, 2004-
Scope and Contents
The records of NOW-New York State, founded in February, 1967, span the years 1966-88 with the bulk of information dating from 1974. Found in the records are minutes of meetings, correspondence, amicus briefs, programs, cassettes, and feminist literature arranged in the following record series: State Council Meetings (1974-88), President's Subject Files (1968-88), Issues Files (1966-85), Lobbyists' Files (1976-88), Mailing Lists (1982-84), Chapter Newsletters (1982-84), and a Feminist Publications Collection (1966-85). Conspicuously absent from the records are files from the early years of the organization; also there are no State Council chairs' files or Executive Committee records. NOW-NYS has concentrated on educational and political activities both for and on behalf of women and women's rights.
The activities of the New York Chapter include, but are not limited to, such areas as lobbying at the State Capitol; monitoring the State Education Department to insure compliance with Title IX which forbids sex discrimination in schools; working in the area of domestic violence and battered women; monitoring the Division of Human Rights to determine whether women are fairly represented in employment discrimination complaints; working to preserve historic sites which have significance to women; helping women enter the work force for the first time; and lobbying for lesbian and reproductive rights.
NOW-NYS consistently shows a concern for women and for education, a term which can refer to grade levels from kindergarten through college; to concerns within the educational system such as equality, sexism, discrimination in textbooks (1970-75); to programs such as Project Move or Project Voice (1981) or the displaced homemakers' programs of the later 1980s. It appears that the educational focus expanded from white collar to blue collar issues in the 1980s. The organization has a two-pronged education plan: to inform its members, and other women and men, about women's issues and rights through both educational and political avenues; and to prepare women to exercise those rights through job training programs and the like.
The organization has a Vice-President for Legislation who is involved in lobbying efforts in Albany. Legislative issues of concern to the organization are clearly identified. The topics become more specific and focused as the organization matures. For example, marriage and divorce issues of the early 1980s become more specifically identified as issues such as orders of protection and imposed joint custody and surrogate parenting in the later 1980s. Concerns expand from equal employment (1972-75) to pay equity (1984-88). The Equal Rights Amendment (1972-88, with gaps) was regularly addressed.
Some issues have been on-going concerns. Women's rights in the areas of health care and of marriage, divorce, child custody, reproduction, and domestic relations head the list of family oriented matters. In the area of employment, the organization has pursued job discrimination, sex discrimination, and pay inequalities. In various years NOW-NYS has tackled social issues including women against women (1971-74); toys and toymakers 1971-74); television portrayals of women (1973-74); prostitution (1975-76) lesbian and gay rights (1978-83); pornography, sexual assault and battering (1983-88); homelessness by divorce (1984-85).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: State Council Meeting Files, 1974-1988
Series 2: President's Subject Files, 1968-1988
Series 3: Issues Files, 1966-1985
Series 4: Lobbyist Files, 1972-1988
Series 5: Mailing Lists, 1982-1984
Series 6: Chapter Newsletter File, 1982-1984
Series 7: Feminist Publications Collection, 1966-1985
Series arrangement statement: SUNY will complete.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by NOW-NYS in 1987. Additional accessions were received from the Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America in 1996, 1999, and 2004. An accession of 30 cubic feet, which is not yet described, was transferred to the Department in April-May 2004.
Access
Access to membership lists in Series 2 is restricted. All other series are unrestricted. Consult a staff member for further details.
Women; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Athletics and Sports; Birth control--New York (State); Abortion services--Law and legislation--New York (State); Equal rights amendments.; Womens rights--New York (State); Homosexuality--Law and legislation--New York (State); Lobbying--New York (State); National Organization for Women.
- State Council Meeting Files, 1974-1988; 1; 1.33 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Scope and Contents
  The State Council Meetings include meeting minutes, cassette recordings of some State Council meetings, memoranda, agendas, correspondence, bylaws, meeting registration lists, newsletters, and some State Convention and State Executive Committee minutes. The State Council Meetings document the structure, function, and activities of the state and local chapters, issues of concern to NOW-NYS on subjects ranging from abortion to education, and provide insight into the running of this state-wide women's network.
  - State Council Meetings (Includes New York State bylaws adopted Nov. 1974.) (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 1)
  - State Council Meetings, 1975 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 2)
  - State Council Meetings (Includes newsletter announcing "First full-fledged NOW New York State convention", Dec.4-5,1976.) (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 3)
  - State Council Meetings, 1976 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 4)
  - State Council Meetings--Agenda (Includes "A Women's Bill of Rights--1976", an act (s9076/a11555, Mar 25, 1976) concerning domestic relations law, a summary of NOW-NYS 1975 Council activities.), 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 5)
  - State Council--Miscellaneous Includes 1978 NOW-NYS legislative program.), 1977-1979 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 6)
  - State Council Meetings, 1976 December-1977 July (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 7)
  - State Council Meetings, 1977 September-1977 November (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 8)
  - State Executive and Council Meetings, 1977 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 9)
  - State Council Meetings--Agenda, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 10)
  - State Council Meetings--Attendance, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 11)
  - State Executive Committee Meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 12)
  - State Council Meetings, 1978 January-1979 May (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 13)
  - State Council Meetings, 1977-1979 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 14)
  - State Council Meetings, 1979 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 15)
  - State Council Meetings (Includes resume and two testimonies of Lorna Rissier Bernard, Emergency Fuel Office Counsel; testimony by John Edwards, Deputy Director, NYS Emergency Fuel Office (1976).), 1979 April-1979 July (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 16)
  - State Council Meetings (Includes Model Chapter Bylaws, NOW, adopted Feb 25, 1978; resolutions to be considered at the 1979 National Conference.), 1979 August-1979 September (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 17)
  - State Council Meetings (Includes articles about Margaret Sanger in Celebration in Poughkeepsie Journal, Sept. 9, 1979.), 1979 September-1979 November (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 18)
  - State Council Meetings (Cassettes), 1980 July 19-1980 July 20 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 19)
  - State Council Meetings (Cassettes), 1980 September 13-1980 September 14 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 20)
  - State Council Meetings (Cassettes), 1980 November 8-9 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 21)
  - State Council Meetings, 1980 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 22)
  - State Council Meetings, 1980 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 23)
  - State Council--Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 24)
  - State Council Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 25)
  - State Council Meetings, 1981 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 26)
  - State Council Meetings, 1981 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 27)
  - State Council Meetings (Cassettes), 1981 January 10-11 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 28)
  - State Council Meetings (Cassettes), 1981 March 14-1981 March 15 (Box 1 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 29)
  - State Council Meetings (Cassettes), 1981 May 3 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 1)
  - State Council Meetings--Attendance Lists, 1979-1982 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 2)
  - State Council Meetings, 1982 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 3)
  - State Council Meetings, 1982 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 4)
  - State Council Meetings (Includes NOW-NYS Bylaws), 1983 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 5)
  - State Council Meetings (Includes memo from Lillian Kozak, chair NOW-NYS Domestic Relations Task Force to all members opposing Bill a4824/s3785 regarding denial of wives' rights in vested but unmatured pensions; information about NOW-NYS convention Apr 7, 1984.) (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 6)
  - State Council Meetings, 1985 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 7)
  - State Council Meetings, 1986 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 8)
  - State Council Meetings, 1987 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 9)
  - State Council Meetings, 1988 (Box 2 (1-State Council Meeting Files), Folder 10)
- President's Subject Files, 1968-1988; 2; 12 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject for a specific year or group of years. Multi-year folders are grouped by the first year in the folder.
  The President's Subject Files of the New York State Chapter of the National Organization for Women include internal and external correspondence, amicus briefs, memoranda, news releases, mailings, newsletters, pamphlets, booklets, minutes, agendas, financial reports, membership lists, by-laws, cassettes, etc. The President's Subject Files document the structure, function, and activities of the state and local chapters; present issues of concern to NOW-NYS on subjects including abortion and reproductive rights (1975-1988), battered women and domestic violence (1976-1988), Bork nomination (1987-1988), education (including educational opportunities for women, sexual discrimination, etc.) (1975-1983), and subsequently job training and displaced homemakers program (1983-1988), Equal Rights Amendment (1976-1988, with gaps), employment (1968-1973), feminization of poverty (1982), homelessness by divorce (1986), lesbian and gay rights (1978-1983), marriage and divorce (1979-1988), parental leave (1987), pay equity (1987), sex discrimination (1979-1980, 1985), sexual harrassment (1987), surrogate parenting (1987-1988), task forces (1971-1987) on the following: consciousness raising (1980-1981), domestic relations law (1978-1983), education (1981-1982), employment (1981), marriage and divorce (1981), pornography, sexual assault and battering (1983-1988); and provide an account of lobbying and legislative issues promoted by NOW. Correspondents include NOW-NYS presidents and officials, NOW-NYS chapter leaders, political candidates and politicians, state officials, etc.
  - Albany Area Now, 1972-1975 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Bank statements--Security Trust, 1974-1977 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Bylaws, 1974-1978 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - By-laws & National Officers, 1973 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - By-laws (NYS), 1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - By-laws Pennsylvania, 1973 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Chapters, 1972-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Albany, 1972
  - Central New York, 1972
  - Elizabeth Cady Stanton (Seneca Falls), 1974
  - Erie County Surburban Chapter, 1973-1974
  - Finger Lakes, 1974
  - Genesee Valley (Rochester), 1974
  - Glens Falls, 1974
  - Jamestown, 1974
  - Jefferson County, 1973
  - Knolls, 1974
  - Liverpool, 1974
  - Mid-Hudson, 1974
  - Newburgh (Orange County Feminist Union), 1974
  - Northern Chautauqua, 1974
  - Oneonta (Delaware County), 1974
  - Orleans County, 1974
  - Plattsburgh, 1974
  - Schenectady, 1974
  - Staten Island (Richmond), 1974
  - South Shore, 1974
  - Suffolk, 1974
  - Troy, 1974
    Conditions Governing Access
    Item is restricted, please consult an archivist for details.
  - Chapters, Applications & Lists of Meetings Conveniened, 1972-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Chapters, Organization of, 1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Chapters, Organization of, and By-laws, 1972-1976 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Compliance with Equal Employment Opportunities Act, 1971 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Conferences, 1973-1977 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Do It Now, 1971-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Education, 1968-1972 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Education, 1973-1975 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Elections--National NOW, 1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Elections--National NOW, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Employment, 1968-1973 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Employment--Manual, Undated (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Forms, Undated (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Graham, Judy (National Business Manager), 1974-1976 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Latino American Committees established, ca. 1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Mailing list, [undated] Mailings from National Office, 1971-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Membership print-out, 1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Mid-Hudson Chapter NOW news releases, 1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Molnar, Sheila, 1973-1975 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - National Board, 1971-1975 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - National Office, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - National Women's Day, August 26, 1970-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - New York City Chapter NOW news releases, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - News Releases and Programs, 1970-1981 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - Organizational Guide & Information, 1970-1974 (Box 1 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - Pennsylvania NOW, 1973 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Queens Chapter NOW news releases, 1974 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Resolutions, 1966; 1970; 1974 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Staten Island Chapter NOW news releases, 1974 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Suffolk N.O.W. Chapter news releases, 1974 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Task force heads, 1971 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Task forces, 1971-1974 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Treasury--Laura Rosman, 1974 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Abortion, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Albany Area NOW, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Alice Doesn't--women's strike, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Assertiveness training, June, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Chapters, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Chapters, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Child Care, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, outgoing, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Do It NOW, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Education, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Law suits, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Legal Policy and Guide, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Legislative Office, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Majority caucus, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Media reform, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Membership, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - National Office, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Rape, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Regional Conference--Philadelphia, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Resolutions, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - State Conference--Mailing lists, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - State Conference--Ossining, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - State Conference packet, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - State Council, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 34)
  - Stockholder's action, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 35)
  - Task forces, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 36)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 37)
  - Women's Unit--Executive Chamber, 1975 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 38)
  - Andrews Zelle, 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 39)
  - Andrews, Zelle, 1976-1978 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 40)
  - Battered Women, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 41)
  - By-laws, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 42)
  - Chapters, 1976-1980 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 43)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 44)
  - Do It Now, 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 45)
  - Eastern Region State Coordinators, 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 46)
  - Equal Rights Amendment, 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 47)
  - Graham, Judy (Business Manager), 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 48)
  - Lists--chapters, delegates, etc., 1976-1978 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 49)
  - Membership, at-large, 1976-1980 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 50)
  - Membership dues, 1976 (Box 2 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - National NOW Board, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - National NOW Conference, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, 1976-1977 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Press clippings, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Reproduction, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Resolutions, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Task forces, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1976 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Abortion, 1977-1978 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Battered women, 1977-1979 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Budget, 1977-1978 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Budget, 1977-1980 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Budget, dues, forms, 1977-1980 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Carey, Gov. U. L.--Endorsement, 1978 (Box 3 (2-President's Subject Files), Folder 15)